i am a widow
나는 과부입니다
i know
나도 알아
You are the king of this country
당신은 이 나라의 왕입니다
i don't care
난 상관없어
People will scold me and ridicule me for being unruly.
사람들은 내가 무질서하다고 꾸짖고 비웃을 것입니다.
Whatever they say
그들이 뭐라고 말하든
Let's go
가자
Don't hold that hand
그 손을 잡지 마세요
you can't go
넌 갈 수 없어
until death
죽을 때까지
You can only stay at this home
당신은 이 집에만 머물 수 있어요
get out of the way
길을 비켜라
Different from the noble Maharaja
고귀한 마하라자와는 다르다
It's easy for me to be mean
내가 못된 짓을 하는 건 쉬운 일이야
She is the woman of this family
그녀는 이 집안의 여자이다
I won't be able to leave this house until I die.
나는 죽을 때까지 이 집에서 나갈 수 없을 것이다.
if i become mean
내가 못되게 굴면
Except for Hong Eun-jo, this family
홍은조 빼고 이 가족은
I will kill them all to get her out of this house.
나는 그녀를 이 집에서 꺼내기 위해 그들을 모두 죽일 것이다.
jujube sword
대추 검
Let's have a try
한번 해보자
Forget about official rank and identity
공식적인 지위와 정체성은 잊어라
Put away the gift
선물을 치워두세요
Are you a good fighter?
당신은 좋은 전사인가요?
You talk too much
당신은 말을 너무 많이 해요
What are you doing? Come on.
뭐하는 거야? 어서 해봐요.
If someone creates trouble, I will stay with you till the end.
누군가 문제를 일으키면 나는 끝까지 당신과 함께 있을 것입니다.
I'm quite satisfied with this
나는 이것에 꽤 만족한다.
Judge Xu, are you just going to stand by and watch?
Xu 판사님, 그냥 서서 지켜보실 건가요?
Men grow up fighting
남자들은 싸우면서 자란다
if i win
내가 이기면
Hong Eun-jo will die at my house
홍은조가 우리집에서 죽는다
Hong Enzu will live forever in my house
홍엔즈는 우리 집에서 영원히 살 것이다
So childish
너무 유치해
I said two
2개라고 했는데
It's up to me where I want to die.
어디에서 죽고 싶은지는 나에게 달려 있다.
Agree?
동의하다?
Agree
동의하다
If either of you dares to swing a sword...
둘 중 한 사람이라도 감히 칼을 휘두른다면...
Swordsmanship is good
검술이 좋다
Good strength
좋은 힘
what is this doing
이게 뭐하는 거야?
Lord Superintendent
주 교육감
How come you are here...
어쩌다 여기까지 왔니...
Eunjo, come with me
은조야 나랑 같이 가자
Oh my god
맙소사
What to do
해야 할 일
what is this sound
이게 무슨 소리야?
Is dad back?
아빠는 돌아오셨나요?
Master, go and persuade him.
선생님, 가서 설득해 보세요.
Dad…
아빠…
You…
당신은…
I knew it would be like this
난 이렇게 될 줄 알았어
After all, you still treat Dad...
그래도 넌 여전히 아빠를 대하는구나...
Dad
아빠
Please stop in moderation
적당히 멈춰주세요
It's all my fault as a father who is incompetent
다 내 탓이다 무능력한 아버지
Father?
아버지?
It's because you treat evil girls as your own children
나쁜 여자를 자기 자식처럼 대하기 때문이야
That's why she would act so wantonly
그래서 그녀는 그렇게 제멋대로 행동했지
She is the one who once got married without telling us
우리한테도 말하지 않고 결혼한 적이 있는 사람이에요
Even now
지금도
I will discipline her well
나는 그 사람을 잘 징계할 것이다.
treat her as a slave
그녀를 노예로 대하다
Come out
나오다
Do you think I can't do it?
내가 할 수 없을 것 같아?
get out of the way
길을 비켜라
Really useless
정말 쓸모없어
I've had enough
난 충분히 먹었어
When did you start standing there?
언제부터 거기 서기 시작했어요?
Been there from the beginning
처음부터 거기 있었어
You go
당신은 간다
I don't want to look so close to you
난 당신을 그렇게 가까이 보고 싶지 않아요
Agree
동의하다
Won't you leave?
떠나지 않을래?
This is my home
여기가 내 집이야
Please think about who is more reasonable to stand next to the wall
벽 옆에 서는 것이 누가 더 합리적인지 생각해 보세요.
You should also think about who is more handsome standing next to the wall
벽 옆에 서있는 사람이 더 잘생긴 것도 생각해보세요
The duel is not over yet
결투는 아직 끝나지 않았다
This victory or defeat does not depend on the sword, it is left to the judges to decide.
이 승패는 칼에 달려 있는 것이 아니라 심판의 몫이다.
You chose the wrong opponent
상대를 잘못 선택했네
Really? My strength has never failed.
정말요? 내 힘은 한 번도 실패한 적이 없습니다.
I never give up
난 절대 포기하지 않아
Sorry to interrupt the fight between you two.
두 분의 싸움을 방해해서 죄송합니다.
You have to stand here until one of them leaves.
그들 중 한 명이 떠날 때까지 여기 서 있어야 해요.
Could this be some kind of self-esteem contest?
일종의 자존심 대결이 아닐까?
Of course not
물론 아니지
Absolutely not
절대 아니다
The two of you have been standing here for more than half an hour. Your feet must be numb.
두 분은 30분 넘게 여기 서 계셨습니다. 발이 마비되어야합니다.
My back must be hurting too, right?
허리도 아프겠지?
Okay, so be it
알았어, 그럼 됐지
I counted to three and we both left at the same time.
나는 셋까지 세었고 우리 둘은 동시에 떠났다.
Okay one
알았어 하나
Two
2개
three
세
three point five
3점 5점
Four
4개
They actually refused to give in to each other and didn't leave until four.
그들은 실제로 서로 양보하기를 거부했고 4시까지 떠나지 않았습니다.
Childish showdown ends in a draw
유치한 대결은 무승부로 끝났다
Oops, my hands are so sore
아 손이 너무 아프다
After learning the truth on the wedding day, I was the one who still asked her to get married.
결혼식 날 진리를 알게 된 뒤에도 여전히 그 사람에게 결혼하자고 한 사람은 바로 나였습니다.
Please blame me
나를 비난해주세요
where is eunjo
은조는 어디 있어?
I let her go out
나는 그녀를 밖으로 내보내었다
I asked her to go outside to calm down her restless heart.
나는 그녀에게 불안한 마음을 진정시키기 위해 밖으로 나가라고 요청했습니다.
(empty streets the lights are low)
(텅 빈 거리의 불빛은 어둡다)
(shadows play a quiet show)
(그림자가 조용한 쇼를 하고 있다)
Come and see
와서 보세요
Let's take a look at the accessories before leaving.
떠나기 전 악세사리를 살펴보겠습니다.
Miss
미스
This way please
이쪽으로 부탁드려요
Oops, how about this?
이런, 이건 어때요?
Come and see
와서 보세요
Oh my God, my face has brightened up.
맙소사, 얼굴이 밝아졌어요.
Simply made for you
당신을 위해 간단하게 만들어졌습니다.
So beautiful
너무 아름다워
My complexion has improved.
안색이 좋아졌어요.
Oh, it’s like a fairy descended to earth
아, 마치 요정이 지구에 내려온 것 같아
(I've seen the scene)
(나는 그 장면을 본 적이 있다)
(played it back in every dream)
(꿈에서마다 다시 재생함)
Want to play?
놀고 싶어?
Swing very, very high
아주 아주 높게 스윙하세요
Leave all your worries and sorrows in heaven and come back again
모든 걱정과 슬픔을 천국에 맡기고 다시 오세요
I don't want to play
나는 놀고 싶지 않다
(seen the scene)
(현장을 보았다)
(echoes in the hallway light)
(복도 조명에 울려퍼짐)
(memories that won't feel right)
(제대로 느껴지지 않는 기억)
(I stay quiet you fade slow)
(난 조용히 있어, 넌 천천히 사라져)
(same old scene I used to know)
(내가 알던 똑같은 장면)
Hong Shi seems to be fine
홍시 괜찮은거같아
Not so
그렇지 않다
Because it's all buried
다 묻혀있으니까
Buried in the words "It doesn't matter"
상관없어'라는 말 속에 묻혀
She just buries it
그 사람은 그냥 묻어버려
All buried under the expression "It doesn't matter"
상관없다는 표현 아래 모두 묻혀버렸어
(I've seen the scene)
(나는 그 장면을 본 적이 있다)
(everything is gone)
(모든 것이 사라졌습니다)
(and still it speaks)
(그리고 아직도 말하고 있어)
(seen the scene)
(현장을 보았다)
Go look elsewhere
가서 다른 곳을 찾아보세요
why do you follow me
왜 나를 따라오나요?
I want to say…
나는 말하고 싶다…
If you fall into a ditch, I'll pull you up
도랑에 빠지면 내가 끌어올려줄게
If you drink I'll pour you a drink
네가 마시면 내가 부어줄게
If you cry I will pat you
울면 토닥여줄게
when did you discover
언제 발견했어요?
How can you hide if you are so tall?
키가 크면 어떻게 숨길 수 있나요?
I bent over hard
나는 세게 몸을 굽혔다
Still discovered?
아직도 발견되었나요?
I wrote to Supervisor Hong Minzhi because...
홍민지 감독님께 편지를 쓴 이유는...
for what reason
무슨 이유로
I am just a king of a country
나는 단지 한 나라의 왕일 뿐이다
Correct a wrong marriage
잘못된 결혼을 바로잡아라
Just to correct the unethical customs
비윤리적인 관습을 바로잡기 위해
You are so righteous and awe-inspiring, but you are sending a letter in my name?
당신은 이렇게 의롭고 경이로운 분이신데 내 이름으로 편지를 보내시나이까?
Is there any
거기에 있나요
When I write this letter, my soul is in your body
이 편지를 쓸 때 내 영혼은 당신 몸 안에 있어요
I probably wrote your name accidentally.
아마 실수로 이름을 썼을 거예요.
I wrote my name with my hands
손으로 이름을 썼어요
i know
나도 알아
I made my own decision again
난 또 내 마음대로 결정을 내렸어
Punch me. I'm very durable.
나를 때려주세요. 나는 매우 내구성이 있습니다.
But be a little lighter
하지만 좀 더 가벼워지세요
Forget it
잊어 버려
i can understand
나는 이해할 수 있다
You were so close to living as a widow forever in this body.
당신은 이 몸에서 영원히 과부로 살기에 너무나 가까웠습니다.
Of course I have to find a way to leave that home.
물론 나는 그 집을 떠날 방법을 찾아야 한다.
Anyway, I should face this matter sooner or later
어쨌든, 이 문제는 조만간 직면해야 할 것 같아요
But how lucky
하지만 얼마나 운이 좋은지
Fortunately, my body recovered in time
다행히 시간이 지나면서 몸이 회복됐어요
Are you really okay?
정말 괜찮아요?
That's good
그거 좋다
This is my marriage proposal
이건 내 결혼 제안이야
And…
그리고…
Since you said it's okay
네가 괜찮다고 말했으니까
That's enough for today
오늘은 그걸로 충분해
I'm short on money. Sorry I can't help.
나는 돈이 부족해요. 죄송해요. 도와드릴 수가 없어요.
I am the one who made the unkind request and apologized.
불친절한 요청을 하고 사과한 사람은 바로 저입니다.
Wait a minute, my lord
잠깐만요, 주인님
Isn't this my cousin?
이 사람은 내 사촌 아닌가요?
I originally planned to visit your home after finishing my business in Seoul.
원래는 서울에서 사업을 마치고 당신 집을 방문할 계획이었어요.
I didn't expect to meet you here
여기서 당신을 만날 줄은 몰랐어요
If you delay any longer, it will be too late.
더 이상 지체하면 너무 늦습니다.
thank you
감사합니다
This is to repay the favor of saving lives on the battlefield.
이는 전장에서 생명을 구한 은혜에 보답하기 위함이다.
You are Eunjo, right?
당신이 은조 맞죠?
Yes
예
No need to send far
멀리 보낼 필요 없어
Tell the benefactor thank you for his hospitality
후원자에게 환대에 감사하다고 전하세요.
OK
알았어
Enzu
엔즈
It's all over now
이제 다 끝났어
what does this mean
이게 무슨 뜻이야?
I have followed my instructions and said it was the money earned from selling the land.
나는 지시에 따라 땅을 팔아 번 돈이라고 말했습니다.
This matter must be kept confidential
이 문제는 비밀로 유지되어야 합니다
Can you please tell me the reason?
이유를 알려주실 수 있나요?
I hope that person feels better
그 사람 기분이 좋아졌으면 좋겠어
what
뭐
I heard that the year of Gengwu
경무년이라고 들었는데
All the property of Eunuch Hong Minzhi was confiscated by the royal family
홍민지 내시 재산을 모두 왕실에 압수당하다
Just think of it as returning it now.
그냥 지금 돌려준다고 생각하세요.
Lord Superintendent
주 교육감
where have you been
어디 있었어?
sorry
미안
Could it be...
그럴 수도 있지...
You took the land given by Luozhou elders during the day
당신은 낮에 낙주 장로들이 준 땅을 차지했습니다.
Have you given them all to Mr. Du Chengzhi?
Du Chengzhi 씨에게 모두 주었습니까?
Please take it back
다시 가져가주세요
That marriage was my choice...
그 결혼은 내 선택이었어...
it's not your choice
그것은 당신의 선택이 아니다
It's not your responsibility
그건 당신 책임이 아니예요
Not your marriage
당신의 결혼은 아니죠
it's my fault
그건 내 잘못이야
That piece of land is enough to provide you with food and clothing for the rest of your life...
그 땅은 당신이 평생 동안 먹을 것과 입을 것을 제공하기에 충분합니다.
enough
충분히
Stop humiliating yourself
자신을 모욕하지 마세요
I never looked at you that way
난 당신을 그런 식으로 쳐다본 적이 없어요
If you really think about me
당신이 정말로 나를 생각한다면
Just value yourself first
자신을 먼저 소중히 여기세요
Forget everything that happened in that home
그 집에서 일어난 일은 다 잊어버려
forgive me
용서해줘
Forgive your stupid father
멍청한 아버지를 용서하세요
Since you told me to forget
잊어버리라고 한 이후로
I have forgotten everything
나는 모든 것을 잊었다
Are you hungry?
배고프나요?
I'm going to help my mother prepare dinner
나는 어머니가 저녁 식사 준비하는 것을 도와드릴 예정입니다.
Daoyue Dajun
도웨다준
Are you the one who summoned Superintendent Hong Minzhi?
홍민지 교육감을 소환한 사람이 당신인가요?
He was once the military judge of this country
그는 한때 이 나라의 군사판사였습니다.
It is said that countless battles have been won in the north.
북쪽에서는 수많은 전투에서 승리했다고 합니다.
As a gentleman living in the land he protects
자신이 지키는 땅에 사는 신사로서
Pray that he is okay
그가 괜찮기를 기도해
Pray for his family’s safety
그의 가족의 안전을 위해 기도해주세요
It's a matter of course
당연한 일이죠
Isn’t it because of Hong Shi?
홍시 때문 아닌가?
I'm just praying that the daughter of the military judge is safe
군판사의 딸이 무사하길 기도할 뿐입니다
It happens to be Hong Eun-jo
홍은조인가봐요
I mean, it’s for Dr. Hong.
내 말은, 홍 박사님을 위한 거라는 거죠.
what to do how to
무엇을 어떻게 해야 할까?
Hong Minzhi Supervisor
홍민지 감독관
He was the one who was ruthlessly abandoned by His Highness in the year of Gengwu.
그는 경무년에 전하에게 무자비하게 버림받은 사람이었습니다.
When it comes to the relationship between families, it is no different from a feud
가족간의 관계는 불화와 다르지 않다
thank you
감사합니다
Came back just in time
시간에 딱 맞춰 돌아왔어
Go to work
일하러 가세요
Yes
예
That damn marriage fell through
그 망할 결혼은 파탄났어
I feel relieved both physically and mentally
몸도 마음도 편안해지는 기분이에요
From now on, I can have a glass of wine at ease when I’m on duty.
이제부터는 근무시간에 편하게 와인 한잔 할 수 있겠네요.
What is there to be happy about?
기뻐할 일이 뭐가 있겠습니까?
I happen to want to have a drink with you, madam.
마침 당신과 한잔 하고 싶은데요, 부인.
What ma'am?
무슨 부인?
What's wrong, you kid?
무슨 일이야, 꼬마야?
madam boy
마담 보이
Madam
부인
Man... son...
이봐... 아들...
It's so noisy
너무 시끄러워요
Eunjo, that's great
은조야, 그거 좋지
Have you two seen a doctor?
두 분은 의사를 만나보셨나요?
Oh…
아…
I have a dull pain in my stomach. I'm afraid it's because of the epidemic.
배에 둔한 통증이 있습니다. 전염병 때문일까 두렵습니다.
That's because I have stomachache due to constipation.
변비로 인해 배가 아프기 때문이죠.
I was so dizzy that I thought I had an epidemic.
너무 어지러워서 전염병이 걸린 줄 알았어요.
That's a hangover
그거 숙취야
You saw it last time, right?
지난번에 보셨죠?
Half of the recent patients are like this
최근 환자의 절반이 이렇습니다.
Unfounded rumors are really rampant in the capital.
수도에는 근거 없는 소문이 정말 만연해 있습니다.
Speaking of which, it’s really serious outside the city.
그러고 보니 도시 밖은 정말 심각하네요.
There was an epidemic
전염병이 일어났어요
If the epidemic spreads to the capital, people's morale will be in chaos
전염병이 수도까지 퍼지면 사람들의 사기는 혼란에 빠질 것입니다
Don’t epidemics happen every year?
전염병은 매년 발생하지 않나요?
Just let it go and it will disappear naturally
그냥 놔두면 자연스럽게 사라져요
Compared with that, every time His Highness goes to Wenyang Palace for hunting,
이에 비해 전하께서는 문양궁에 사냥하러 갈 때마다
The court remains vacant for longer and longer periods of time
법원은 점점 더 오랜 기간 동안 비어 있습니다.
I'm thinking it's better to open a hunting ground near the capital.
수도 근처에 사냥터를 여는 게 좋을 것 같아요.
The area around the capital city is full of people’s residences and cultivated land.
수도 주변 지역은 주민들의 주거지와 경작지로 가득하다.
Absolutely not
절대 아니다
Please make an appointment before coming over
오시기 전에 약속을 잡아주세요
Your Majesty has left the palace
폐하께서 궁궐을 떠나셨습니다
Please tell your majesty that I am seeking to see you about my little daughter.
제가 제 어린 딸에 관해 당신을 만나려고 한다고 폐하께 말씀해 주십시오.
I've been coughing all day
하루 종일 기침을 했어요
You should go to the inner hospital
내과병원으로 가셔야 해요
My exclusive doctor went to the palace with me
내 전담 의사가 나와 함께 궁에 갔어
I've had asthma for a long time, I've had it since I was a child
나는 오랫동안 천식을 앓았고, 어렸을 때부터 겪었습니다.
I've used that body, so I know it clearly
나는 그 몸을 써봤기 때문에 확실히 안다.
That's a healthy physique with nothing wrong with it
흠잡을 곳 하나 없는 건강한 몸매네요
It started a few days ago
며칠 전부터 시작됐어요
You were injured in the last fight, right?
지난번 싸움에서 부상을 당하셨죠?
Let me see
좀 보자
No injuries
부상 없음
Just a little itchy
조금 가려울 뿐이야
I'm more worried about that guy
난 그 사람이 더 걱정돼
I'm so hurt
너무 아파요
He probably took a walk on Huangquan Road.
아마도 황취안로(Huangquan Road)를 산책했을 것입니다.
So why fight?
그럼 왜 싸워요?
Encountering someone who is deliberately looking for trouble
일부러 문제를 일으키려는 사람을 만나는 것
Ignoring him is the right thing to do
그를 무시하는 것이 옳은 일이다
That person is so twisted that it makes people feel pitiful
그 사람은 너무 일그러져서 사람이 불쌍해질 정도야
So you think the Ren family didn't let you go on purpose?
그럼 렌 가족이 고의로 당신을 놓아주지 않았다고 생각하시나요?
Otherwise?
그렇지 않으면?
The more you know, the more twisted things will become
알면 알수록 일이 꼬이게 돼
Do you want to go to dinner?
저녁 먹으러 갈래?
So suddenly?
갑자기?
Didn't you work all day?
하루종일 일 안 했어?
There are no patients here
여기는 환자가 없어요
You don't have a family either
너도 가족이 없잖아
No more husband
더 이상 남편이 없습니다
Your stomach is empty, right?
속이 텅 비었지요?
It turns out that he came here because he knew I had broken off the engagement.
알고 보니 그 사람은 내가 파혼한 것을 알고 여기까지 온 것이었습니다.
Could it be...
그럴 수도 있지...
Your Majesty?
폐하?
I thought I saw it wrong
내가 잘못 본 줄 알았는데
I can actually see you here
실제로 여기서 당신을 볼 수 있어요
Have you used my body to meet other women?
내 몸을 이용해 다른 여자를 만나본 적 있나요?
Not me
나 말고
You really don’t remember
너 정말 기억 못 하잖아
I am the daughter of Han Seung-rok, the leader of the Council. My name is Ji-yeon.
저는 협의회 의장인 한승록의 딸입니다. 제 이름은 지연이에요.
Ah, I saw you in the palace last time
아, 저번에 궁에서 봤어
yes
응
I also heard that the Maharaja
마하라자(Maharaja)도 들었다.
Rejected all the ladies in the capital
수도의 모든 여자들을 거부했어요
How come you are here?
왜 여기에 왔어요?
I heard there is an epidemic
전염병이 있다고 들었어
My father asked me to send some medicinal materials to the Huimin Department
아버지께서 나에게 희민과에 약재를 좀 보내달라고 하셨다.
As expected of the Prime Minister
총리의 예상대로
Say hello to him for me
나를 위해 그 사람에게 안부 전해주세요.
I will
나는 할 것이다
Why is it so heavy?
왜 이렇게 무거워요?
give it to me
나에게 줘
Along the way
길을 따라
How about we catch the old hen we made last time?
지난번에 만들었던 늙은 암탉을 잡아보는 건 어떨까요?
what
뭐
Are you going to see my mother?
우리 엄마 보러 갈 거야?
Yes
예
Anyway, I called her "Mother" for a while.
어쨌든 나는 한동안 그녀를 '엄마'라고 불렀다.
Then she can be considered my mother, right?
그러면 그 분은 내 어머니라고 할 수 있겠죠?
Reply to the marriage request letter…
결혼요청서에 답장…
This shouldn't be said here
여기서 이런 말을 해서는 안 된다
Talk about it later
나중에 얘기해
Let's go eat first
먼저 먹으러 가자
No
아니요
you listen to me
당신은 내 말을 들어요
Find someone suitable to be the king of this country.
이 나라의 왕이 되기에 적합한 사람을 찾아보세요.
Why would you look for someone else if you didn't look for someone with intact limbs?
팔다리가 온전한 사람을 찾지 않고 왜 다른 사람을 찾겠습니까?
Who are you looking for?
당신은 누구를 찾고 있나요?
Don't pretend you don't understand
이해하지 못하는 척하지 마세요
Someone like the lady who led the administration
정권을 이끈 아줌마 같은 사람
are you jealous
질투하는 거야?
Not really
별로
Because of my mother-in-law, I had no choice but to meet her once.
시어머니 때문에 한 번 만날 수밖에 없었습니다.
Just once
딱 한 번만
I didn't ask you
나는 당신에게 묻지 않았다
At least pretend to be curious.
적어도 궁금한 척은 해보세요.
I'm saying these things for your own good
나는 당신의 이익을 위해 이런 말을하고 있습니다
If it's really for my own good
그것이 정말로 나 자신을 위한 것이라면
Just go catch the old hen
그냥 가서 늙은 암탉을 잡으세요
If you want to catch an old hen, go and ask the chef from the Royal Kitchen to catch him.
늙은 암탉을 잡고 싶다면 왕실 주방의 셰프에게 가서 잡아달라고 부탁하세요.
Wait, where are you going?
잠깐, 어디로 가는 거야?
This thing hasn't been taken away yet
이 물건은 아직 빼앗기지 않았습니다
If you keep arguing like this again
또 이런 식으로 논쟁을 벌인다면
Let alone a family feud.
가족 불화는 말할 것도 없습니다.
They should probably become enemies directly.
그들은 아마도 직접적으로 적이 될 것입니다.
Love affairs between men and women often end up becoming enemies.
남자와 여자의 사랑은 결국 적이 되는 경우가 많습니다.
That would be more natural
그게 더 자연스러울 텐데
Are you inciting me to do this?
나를 이렇게 하도록 부추기고 있는 겁니까?
Jealousy?
질투?
It's nonsense
말도 안 되는 소리야
If you want to talk about old hen again, just go away.
또 늙은 암탉 얘기를 하고 싶으면 그냥 가세요.
I'm really...oh my god
난 정말...오 맙소사
Doctor Hong, it’s me
홍 박사님, 나예요
Uncle scared me
삼촌이 겁을 줬어
If you want to enter the city, you must wear this cloak.
도시에 들어가려면 이 망토를 입어야 합니다.
If recognized by others
다른 사람이 인정한 경우
On the contrary, it will cause unnecessary commotion...
오히려 불필요한 소란을 일으키게 되는데...
who are you
당신은 누구입니까?
It's someone I know
내가 아는 사람이에요
Why should a man disguise himself as a woman and follow her?
왜 남자가 여자로 변장하고 그녀를 따라가야 합니까?
Something happened at the medical clinic. I want to ask Dr. Hong for help.
진료소에서 무슨 일이 일어났습니다. 홍 박사님에게 도움을 요청하고 싶습니다.
Medical clinic?
진료소?
You said that the epidemic started in the treatment center?
치료센터에서 전염병이 시작됐다고 했죠?
Disease?
질병?
Yesterday, the doctor from the Human Resources Department took a few casual glances and said this
어제 인사부 의사가 몇 번 흘끔 쳐다보더니 이렇게 말했습니다.
Several people have already developed symptoms of vomiting and high fever.
몇몇 사람들은 이미 구토와 고열 증상을 보였습니다.
What's the exact name of the disease?
질병의 정확한 이름은 무엇입니까?
Don't know
모른다
Does it mean it wasn't properly diagnosed?
제대로 진단되지 않았다는 뜻인가요?
This is to respond to the epidemic and help the people.
이는 전염병에 대응하고 사람들을 돕기 위한 것입니다.
Only then did we set up the Department of Living Persons
그제서야 우리는 살아있는 사람 부서를 설립했습니다.
Doctors also reject medical clinics
의사들도 진료소 거부
For sick family members like me
저처럼 몸이 아픈 가족들을 위해
The same goes for people who have to live together
같이 살아야 하는 사람들도 마찬가지야
No one is willing to take care of us except Doctor Hong.
홍 박사 외에는 누구도 우리를 돌보려 하지 않습니다.
Let's go quickly
빨리 가자
Uncle, wait for me
삼촌, 기다려주세요
What's wrong
무슨 일이야?
Here is a cure for all the risks of infection
여기에 감염의 모든 위험에 대한 치료법이 있습니다.
And I am a medical woman who specializes in medicine
그리고 나는 의학을 전문으로 하는 의료인이다.
It's also my responsibility to restrict access here.
여기에 접근을 제한하는 것도 내 책임이다.
Please listen to her
그녀의 말을 들어주세요
I'm leaving
나는 떠난다
jujube
대추
Go and check if you have been to a medical clinic.
가서 진료소에 가본 적이 있는지 확인하십시오.
Who is the doctor at the Department of Living Human Beings?
생활인학과 의사는 누구인가요?
Yes
예
I take people who seem to have the same symptoms
같은 증상이 있는 것 같은 사람들을 데리고 있어요
They were all placed separately
모두 따로 배치되어 있었어요
Let me take a look
좀 보도록 할게요
delicious
맛있다
Oops
이런
Very dirty, spit it out quickly
너무 더러워 빨리 뱉어내
This is our meal
이게 우리 식사야
Brother, are you hungry too?
형님도 배고프세요?
Do you want to share it with you?
당신과 공유하고 싶나요?
This…
이…
The young master who came with you
당신과 함께 온 젊은 주인
On the hillside over there
저기 언덕에
thank you
감사합니다
right
맞아
On the right?
오른쪽에?
come on
어서
There are many here Yes
여기 많아요 예
Jinshi, come down quickly
진시야 빨리 내려와
how is the situation
상황은 어때?
Let's talk as we go
가면서 얘기 좀 하자
I will be back soon
나는 곧 돌아올 것이다
Brother will come again, right?
형님 또 오실거죠?
Good
좋아
Brother?
형?
Has the water taken from the valley gone bad after being left for too long?
계곡 물이 오래 방치되어 상한 걸까요?
The people at the medical center didn’t know
병원 사람들은 몰랐어요
After drinking it, a group of people contracted dysentery.
그것을 마신 후 한 무리의 사람들이 이질에 걸렸습니다.
Notify the Huimin Administration to get the medicinal materials
약재를 구하려면 후이민 행정처에 신고하세요.
I'm afraid it will take some time
시간이 좀 걸릴 것 같아
Lord Superintendent
주 교육감
It seems that you came to the Huimin Office for something urgent.
급한 일이 있어서 희민 사무실에 오신 것 같습니다.
Eunjo, go get busy.
은조야, 가서 바쁘게 지내라.
I want to talk to this young master
이 젊은 스승님과 이야기하고 싶습니다
I won't get into trouble
나는 문제에 빠지지 않을 것이다
Patients at the clinic are waiting
진료실의 환자들이 기다리고 있습니다.
Then I'll leave first
그럼 나 먼저 갈게
I wanted to grab the rope your brother gave me and enter the court.
형이 준 밧줄을 잡고 코트에 들어가고 싶었어요.
As a result, it was completely ruined by my father.
그 결과 아버지에 의해 완전히 망가졌습니다.
I just ruined the wedding
방금 결혼식을 망쳤어
Then I watched her run to the Huimin Office
그리고 나는 그녀가 희민 사무실로 달려가는 것을 지켜보았다.
Did she go to the Huimin Administration Bureau?
그녀는 후이민 행정국에 갔나요?
Oh, she must be a doctor again and mind her own business.
아, 그녀는 다시 의사가 되어 자신의 일에 신경쓰게 될 것입니다.
Instead of worrying about others
남을 걱정하기보다는
Why isn't she worried about me?
그 사람은 왜 나에 대해 걱정하지 않는 걸까?
Bad girl
나쁜 여자
Isn't it pretty good?
꽤 좋지 않나요?
what
뭐
Know how to worry about others
다른 사람을 걱정하는 방법을 알아라
you are back
당신은 돌아왔다
help me prepare tea
내가 차 준비하는 걸 도와줘
Yes
예
I'll send it over quickly
빨리 보내드릴게요
I previously…
나는 이전에…
I failed to recognize you as the adult Maharaja.
나는 당신을 성인 마하라자로 인식하지 못했습니다.
please forgive me for being rude
무례한 나를 용서해주세요
No need to be so formal
너무 형식적일 필요는 없어
Please don’t come to Eunjo again.
다시는 은조에게 오지 마세요.
If it is because of Your Highness...
전하 때문이라면...
please don't try to convince me
제발 나를 설득하려고 하지 마세요
I apologize to you for what happened between you and His Highness.
당신과 전하 사이에 일어난 일에 대해 사과드립니다.
I am sincere every moment...
나는 매 순간 진심이다..
I don’t want that sincerity
그런 진심은 싫다
Your people will be His Highness's hostages
당신의 백성은 전하의 인질이 될 것입니다
If you are sincere, Your Highness will make the best use of it.
성실하시면 전하께서 이를 최대한 활용하실 것입니다.
I will not send Eunjo to a palace where only one person can die
한 사람만 죽을 수 있는 궁궐에 은조를 보내지 않겠다.
If it is through marriage
결혼을 통해서라면
It goes without saying
말할 것도 없이
If it is for this reason
이런 이유라면
Even if I have to leave the palace, I will protect...
비록 궁궐을 떠나더라도 내가 지켜줄게...
No
아니요
Please don't do anything
제발 아무것도 하지 마세요
As long as you protect Eunjo, that's enough
은조만 지켜주면 그걸로 충분해
If I insist on getting married
내가 결혼을 고집한다면
If I ignore everything and still insist on getting married
다 무시하고 계속 결혼만 고집한다면
If you insist, I will threaten Eunjo
고집하면 은조를 협박하겠다
My father will kill himself
아버지가 자살하실 거예요
If you persist regardless of everything
모든 것에도 불구하고 계속한다면
I would kill myself to stop you.
나는 당신을 막기 위해 자살할 것입니다.
I don’t want me to hurt Eunjo too
나도 은조에게 상처를 주고 싶지 않아
Please help me
도와주세요
You are still there
당신은 아직 거기에 있습니다
Where is the medical clinic?
진료소는 어디에 있나요?
All the more urgent treatments are over
그보다 더 긴급한 치료는 다 끝났어
Because the Huimin Administration Department sent enough medicinal materials.
희민행정부에서 약재를 충분히 보내주었기 때문이다.
Fortunately
다행히
Sir Ti Tiao said
Ti Tiao 선생님이 말씀하셨어요.
I used the medicinal materials given by Lord Daoyue to save my shirt.
나는 셔츠를 구하기 위해 도월경이 준 약재를 사용했습니다.
Thousands of instructions and instructions
수천 가지 지침 및 지침
You must be grateful to the royal family
왕족에게 감사해야 합니다.
thank you
감사합니다
That…
그…
What did you and the Superintendent talk about?
감독님과 어떤 이야기를 나눴나요?
Greetings
인사말
He said he had seen me as a child in the palace before
그 사람은 내가 어렸을 때 궁궐에서 본 적이 있다고 하더군요
Although I have no impression
비록 별 인상은 없지만
So does he also know that you are the Maharaja?
그럼 그 사람도 당신이 마하라자라는 걸 알고 있나요?
he knows very well
그 사람은 아주 잘 알아
So that's it
그래서 그게 다야
Right
오른쪽
Jinshi calls you brother and is looking for you
진시가 형이라고 부르며 찾고 있어요
What exactly did you say to him?
그 사람한테 정확히 뭐라고 말했어요?
Maybe I exude too much charm
내가 너무 매력을 발산하는 건 아닐까
It seems like you are spreading your charm everywhere.
곳곳에 매력을 발산하는 것 같아요.
Yes, so that you can receive it
네, 받아보실 수 있도록
The person who discharged it should come back and take it back personally.
배출한 사람이 직접 와서 가져가야 합니다.
Can you take it back? It’s too much after all.
다시 가져갈 수 있나요? 결국 너무 많습니다.
Where does your confidence come from?
당신의 자신감은 어디서 나오는가?
What I learned from royal education courses
왕실교육과정에서 배운 것
It turns out you learned your bluff.
당신이 허세를 배운 것으로 밝혀졌습니다.
what are you laughing at
뭘 보고 웃고 있는 거야?
why you keep laughing
왜 계속 웃어?
No reason
이유 없음
I just want to continue laughing with you
난 그냥 너와 계속 웃고 싶어
I want to laugh as much as I can today
오늘은 마음껏 웃고 싶어
Master, you are here today too
선생님 오늘도 오셨어요
What's wrong
무슨 일이야?
The eldest young master wants me to burn everything in this room
맏형 청년 사부가 이 방에 있는 걸 다 태워달라고 하더군요
Don't burn
태우지 마세요
After all, there is still some warmth left
그래도 아직은 온기가 남아있으니
Yes
예
Oops
이런
marriage invitation letter
결혼초대장
Where did I fall?
내가 어디로 떨어졌나요?
What a careless
정말 부주의하다
what did you lose
무엇을 잃었나요?
nothing
아무것도
I heard that you and the Maharaja met at the Huimin Office
당신과 마하라자가 희민 사무실에서 만났다고 들었습니다
That adult has a warm personality
그 어른은 성격이 따뜻해요.
I have been helped by him many times
나는 그 사람에게 여러 번 도움을 받았습니다.
That's what a royal family should do
그게 왕족이 해야 할 일이야
Yes
예
you should still remember
아직도 기억해야 해
I want to stay in this home forever
나는 이 집에서 영원히 머물고 싶다.
Serving Mother and the Superintendent
어머니와 교육감에게 봉사
I never intended to live my life as a woman
난 여자로 살 생각은 전혀 없었어
Do you still think so now?
지금도 그렇게 생각하시나요?
Yes
예
be sure to do that
꼭 그렇게 하세요
Miss, I'm going in
아가씨, 들어갈게요
A letter from the palace?
궁에서 온 편지요?
Was it written by the Empress of the Middle Temple?
중사황후가 쓴 것인가?
What's wrong
무슨 일이야?
The concubine said she wanted to see me
첩이 나를 보고 싶다고 하더군요
Where is the Maharaja?
마하라자는 어디에 있나요?
Someone has been sent to his dormitory. He will be there soon...
누군가 그의 기숙사로 파견되었습니다. 그는 곧 거기에 올 것이다...
The adults have arrived
어른들이 도착했어요
what do you want to say
무슨 말을 하고 싶은 거야?
Look at your neat and tidy posture
깔끔하고 단정한 자세를 보세요
That's right
그렇죠
Who is coming?
누가 오나요?
I'm not in the mood to see anyone today
오늘은 누구 만날 기분이 아니야
not human
인간이 아니다
He's the only one left in a pair of flighty dogs
그 사람은 날뛰는 개 한 쌍 중에 남은 유일한 사람이야
Hailin of the Shen family has arrived
Shen 가족의 Hailin이 도착했습니다.
Remember it later
나중에 기억해 보세요
This name is the woman you broke up with after a one-night fling.
이 이름은 당신이 하룻밤을 보내고 헤어진 여자입니다.
The younger one is Shen Jia Hailin, the eldest concubine.
동생은 장남인 심가해림(Shen Jia Hailin)이다.
I shouldn’t need to introduce my son, right?
내 아들을 소개할 필요는 없겠죠?
Yes
예
sit down
앉다
I apologize to you first
먼저 사과드립니다
Queen Mother, there is some misunderstanding here
여왕님, 여기에는 오해가 있습니다
I heard she's Nave's niece
그 사람이 Nave의 조카라고 들었어
Are you a lady from the in-laws?
당신은 시댁 출신의 아줌마입니까?
Don't you know?
모르시나요?
you two
너희 둘
I heard that your engagement was broken off not long ago
약혼이 파탄된 지 얼마 안 됐다고 들었는데
Is the Maharaja the reason for breaking off the engagement?
Maharaja가 약혼을 파기하는 이유입니까?
what
뭐
you don't have to answer
대답하지 않아도 돼
The question raised by the empress is very rude.
황후가 제기한 질문은 매우 무례합니다.
She had just been divorced and it was too late to comfort her.
그녀는 방금 이혼했고 그녀를 위로하기에는 너무 늦었습니다.
what are you doing
뭐하는거야?
What happened before was just me bragging
전에 있었던 일은 그냥 자랑이었어
It was me who caused you to do something disgraceful
너한테 불명예스러운 짓을 한 건 나야.
I'll explain it to you separately. Please get up.
따로 설명드리겠습니다. 일어나주세요.
Yes
예
sit down
앉다
I'll keep it short.
짧게 말하겠습니다.
Now that you two have enjoyed it together,
이제 둘이서 즐거웠으니,
Just don't blame who is responsible
책임이 누구에게 있는지 비난하지 마십시오.
Have a wedding
결혼식을 올리세요
Since this is a marriage between in-laws, it is a great joy for the royal family.
이는 시댁의 혼례이기 때문에 왕실에게는 큰 기쁨이 됩니다.
I'm worried that my mother-in-law is holding on to useless hopes
시어머니가 쓸데없는 기대만 품고 계시는 게 걱정이에요
Making things difficult for the innocent in-laws
무고한 시댁 식구들을 힘들게 만드는
I just deliberately said this here
일부러 여기서 이런 말을 했네요
I already belong
나는 이미 속해 있다
Just forget her
그냥 그녀를 잊어버려
I will never forget it in my life
평생 잊지 못할 거예요
this is my answer
이것이 내 대답이다
Go find out when Hong Shi will take sick leave.
홍시가 언제 병가를 낼지 가서 알아보세요.
As soon as she recovers, ask her to come see me immediately
그녀가 회복되는 대로 즉시 나를 만나러 오라고 하세요
Yes
예
You said before that you gave me a stigma
예전에 나한테 낙인찍었다고 했잖아
Is that this?
그거요?
maybe
어쩌면
previous stigma
이전의 낙인
and today's events
그리고 오늘의 이벤트
I'm all sorry
다 미안해
It turns out that it’s the look in the eyes of another woman that already exists in my heart.
알고 보니 그것은 이미 내 마음 속에 존재하는 다른 여자의 눈빛이었다.
Who could it be?
누구일까요?
Who is the woman who shines in his eyes?
그의 눈에 빛나는 여자는 누구입니까?
It's getting better gradually
점차 좋아지고 있어요
thank you
감사합니다
It's really hard work
정말 힘든 일이에요
sister
여동생
What exactly is there
정확히 무엇이 있나요?
Look there
저기 봐
what is that
그게 뭐야?
It's rice
쌀이에요
Our chestnut trees are really producing rice
우리 밤나무는 정말 벼를 생산하고 있어요
These will last at least a year
이는 최소 1년 동안 지속됩니다.
Who gave us such a precious thing
누가 우리에게 이런 귀한 것을 주었는가
Could it be the Maharaja?
마하라자가 아닐까?
Can I really accept it directly?
정말 직접 받아들일 수 있을까?
Of course you have to eat well and cheer up quickly
물론 잘먹고 빨리 기운내야지
The person who sent the rice should also hope so.
쌀을 보낸 사람도 그랬으면 좋겠다.
It’s Ji Tong…
지통이네...
What? Ji Tong?
무엇? 지통?
It seems that he is really a lucky boy
정말 운이 좋은 아이인 것 같아요
Is it Lord Yoshito who takes care of us?
우리를 돌봐주시는 분은 요시토 님인가요?
It is said that he is a thief who steals thousands of stones in one day.
그는 하루에 수천 개의 돌을 훔치는 도둑이라고 합니다.
It seems to be true. It can't be wrong.
그것은 사실인 것 같습니다. 틀릴 리가 없습니다.
Oops, everyone got it wrong
아, 다들 틀렸어
Ji Tong is a thief who knows how to steal food.
지통은 음식을 훔칠 줄 아는 도둑이다.
And…
그리고…
I heard Ji Dong is dead
지동이 죽었다고 들었어
Everyone... are you listening to me?
여러분... 제 말 듣고 있나요?
Sister, has the dead Jidong been resurrected?
언니, 죽은 지동이 부활했어요?
I am a medical woman, so I know very well
저는 의료인이라 잘 압니다.
If you're dead, you're dead. There's no way you can come here.
당신이 죽으면 당신은 죽은 것입니다. 당신이 여기 올 수 있는 방법은 없습니다.
No, Ji Dong will never die.
아니요, 지동은 절대 죽지 않아요.
Now even immortal
이제는 불멸이라도
What should I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
The rumors have become like this again
또 소문이 이렇게 됐어
I thought everyone in the world wanted us dead
난 세상 모든 사람들이 우리가 죽기를 바라는 줄 알았는데
It turns out that there are people who encourage us to live like this
알고보니 이렇게 살라고 권유하는 사람들도 있더라구요
Just like you, Dr. Hong
당신처럼요, Dr. Hong
what
뭐
I didn't do anything
나는 아무것도 하지 않았다
Medical clinic?
진료소?
Move the clinic here
진료소를 여기로 옮기세요
Plus the mountains here
게다가 여기 산도
Set up as a hunting ground
사냥터로 설정
Only in this way can the damage to the houses be minimized.
그래야만 주택의 피해를 최소화할 수 있습니다.
I think so too
나도 그렇게 생각해요
Does the king need a new hunting ground?
왕에게는 새로운 사냥터가 필요한가요?
Whenever the Lord goes out hunting
주님께서 사냥하러 나가실 때마다
Dad has to go to Wenyang Palace for inspection
아빠는 검사를 위해 문양궁에 가야 해요
So much trouble
문제가 너무 많아
Is it because it would be difficult to manage the court if you are too far away from the palace?
궁에서 너무 멀면 궁정관리가 어려워지기 때문일까요?
You kid has grown up
너 꼬마가 다 컸구나
By the way, why did it happen when dad was not around?
그런데 아빠가 없을 때 왜 그런 일이 일어났나요?
A Hong Minzhi appeared and caused this situation
홍민지가 나타나 이런 사태를 일으켰다.
Where did the land he used to pay off his debts come from?
그가 빚을 갚기 위해 사용한 땅은 어디에서 왔습니까?
He said it was his cousin's land
사촌 땅이라고 하더군요
We should really leave that evil girl in our house
진짜 그 나쁜 여자는 우리 집에 놔둬야 해
why do that
왜 그러는가?
Dad is warning Hong Minzhi
아빠가 홍민지에게 경고한다
That girl is like a hostage
그 여자는 인질같아
So as long as he's not his grandfather, that's fine, right?
그럼 그 사람이 할아버지만 아니라면 괜찮겠죠?
what does it mean
그게 무슨 뜻이야?
As long as he promises what he thinks, that's all
그가 생각하는 것을 약속하는 한 그게 전부입니다
What did he think
그는 무슨 생각을 했나요?
You want me to take that vicious girl as my concubine?
그 사악한 여자를 내 첩으로 삼으라는 겁니까?
are you crazy
너 미쳤어?
Wait a minute
잠깐만요
if not for me
나를 위해서가 아니라면
How about you come
당신은 어때요?
I think you won’t be able to see adults for the time being.
당분간 어른들은 못 볼 것 같아요.
It was difficult for him to leave the palace because of his religious beliefs
종교적 신념 때문에 궁궐 밖으로 나가기가 어려웠다
So that's it
그래서 그게 다야
Is the rice for the medical center sent by the Maharaja?
의료센터에 쌀은 마하라자님이 보내주신건가요?
I'm here to say thank you
나는 감사 인사를 하러 왔습니다
Please convey it to me
나에게 전해주세요
Did you hear this?
이 말을 들었나요?
Ji Tong is resurrected
지통이 부활했다
Did he really come back from the dead?
그는 정말 죽음에서 살아났나요?
What's going on? He is immortal.
무슨 일이야? 그는 불멸이다.
Oops... hello...
앗...안녕...
Are the rumors true?
소문이 사실인가요?
What rumors
무슨 소문이 있니?
I heard that he even sent rice to the medical clinic
진료소에 쌀까지 보냈다고 들었는데
Eunjo has been going to the medical clinic frequently recently.
은조는 최근 병원에 자주 다니고 있다.
I wonder if she has ever met Ji Dong
그녀가 지동을 만난 적이 있는지 궁금해요
what did i say
내가 뭐라고 했어?
Our Lord Gildong’s helping hand
우리 길동님의 도움의 손길
Across every corner of North Korea
북한 구석구석
Oh, Lord Yoshidong
아 요시동님
Ji Tong…
지통…
Are you leaving after praying?
기도하고 떠나는 건가요?
Lord Superintendent returns safely
총독님 무사히 귀환
We thank you for coming
와주셔서 감사합니다
You said before that you really wanted to meet my daughter
아까도 내 딸을 꼭 만나고 싶다고 말했잖아
She is my daughter
그 사람은 내 딸이야
I am Hong Eunjo
저는 홍은조입니다
Can you write down your family's names for me?
가족의 이름을 적어 주실 수 있나요?
I want to pray for you
당신을 위해 기도하고 싶어요
thank you so much
정말 고마워요
thank you for your thoughts
당신의 생각에 감사드립니다
I heard that before the Gengwu Year
나는 Gengwu Year 전에 그것을 들었습니다.
All the people have benefited from the great eunuch Hong Minzhi
온 국민이 대내시 홍민지에게서 이익을 얻었습니다.
I am one of them
나는 그들 중 하나입니다
Do you know what kind of person the current king is?
현재의 왕이 어떤 사람인지 아시나요?
I don't know much about people in high positions.
나는 높은 지위에 있는 사람들에 대해 잘 모른다.
I'm just a common man running for a living
나는 그저 먹고살기 위해 달리는 평범한 사람일 뿐이다
you should understand
당신은 이해해야
Because that person once had a knife
그 사람도 한때 칼을 가졌었으니까
Put it on the neck of Hongminzhi Superintendent
홍민지감찰관 목에 걸어주세요
Knife?
칼?
Just in the year of Gengwu...
바로 Gengwu의 해에 ...
that bloody year
그 망할 년
Those people can be punished just by being superior
저 사람들은 우월한 것만으로도 처벌받을 수 있어
It will definitely become a big trouble for His Highness in the future.
앞으로 전하께 큰 문제가 될 것이 분명합니다.
Superintendent Hong Minzhi's advice almost cost him his life
홍민지 교육감의 조언으로 목숨을 잃을 뻔했다
Punishment with the Book of Disobedience
불순종의 책으로 형벌을 내리다
It's a smart move
현명한 움직임이군요
Ren Shiheng, who was just an admonisher at that time,
당시 단지 훈계자였던 Ren Shiheng은 다음과 같이 말했습니다.
Survive on flattery
아첨으로 살아남기
A king who is flattered by treacherous ministers
반역한 신하들의 아첨을 받는 왕
Brutally eradicate those officials who are unwilling to submit to them
복종하지 않는 관료들을 잔인하게 근절하라
And in the name of threatening the throne
그리고 왕좌를 위협한다는 명목으로
Persecution of the late king’s harem and half-brothers
고(故) 왕의 하렘과 이복형에 대한 박해
Rather than live with this humiliation...
이런 치욕을 안고 살기보다는...
Mother
어머니
that year
그 해
The king who dyed his court red with blood
자신의 궁정을 피로 붉게 물들인 왕
and his puppet, the treacherous minister Ren Shiheng
그리고 그의 꼭두각시인 간사한 장관 런시헝(Ren Shiheng)
And those bureaucrats who are like clones
그리고 클론 같은 관료들
Take control of the main hall
본당을 장악하라
Step by step, today's North Korea is pushed to destruction
한걸음 한걸음 지금의 북한은 파멸의 길로 내몰리고 있다
I only know that he angered His Highness by speaking outright.
나는 그가 노골적으로 말함으로써 전하를 화나게 했다는 것만 알고 있습니다.
I didn’t expect to experience that kind of thing in the palace.
궁궐에서 그런 일을 겪을 줄은 몰랐어요.
Don't know if it's normal
정상인지는 모르겠지만
After all, both the royal family and the scholar-bureaucrats kept silent.
결국 왕실과 학자 관료 모두 침묵을 지켰습니다.
So the Superintendent also...
그래서 감독님도..
Why are you telling me this?
왜 나한테 이런 말을 하는 거야?
as children
어린이로서
You should know your father’s history
아버지의 역사를 알아야 해
Supervisor Hong went through that incident
홍 감독님이 그 사건을 겪었어요
Now living a stable life
이제 안정된 삶을 살고 있어요
I feel lucky and respect this
다행이라고 생각하고 존경합니다
Yes
예
I have met Ji Dong in person
지동을 직접 만나봤습니다
Rumors of Ji Tong's resurrection spread among the people
Ji Tong의 부활 소문이 사람들 사이에 퍼졌습니다.
God-like existence…
신과 같은 존재…
Maybe
어쩌면
Really need a god
진짜 신이 필요해
You go and collect all the rumors about Ji Tong
너는 가서 Ji Tong에 대한 모든 소문을 수집하라
I can't rashly ask the eunuch about the Gengwu Year, right?
함부로 환관에게 경오년을 물어볼 수는 없겠죠?
Let's eat
먹자
Why are you eating chicken all of a sudden?
갑자기 치킨은 왜 먹나요?
Don’t you really want to eat the old hens that I slaughtered with my own hands?
내가 직접 도살한 늙은 암탉을 정말 먹고 싶지 않니?
what
뭐
Oops, scared me
아, 겁이 났어
What's wrong
무슨 일이야?
Is it because I only had half left after I gave it to the Superintendent?
교육감님께 드리고 반밖에 남지 않아서 그런걸까요?
It’s the old hen again
또 늙은 암탉이네
When did I ask you to kill the old hen?
내가 언제 너한테 그 늙은 암탉을 죽여달라고 했어?
What you said last time
지난번에 말씀하신 것
Why do you seem to be a different person?
왜 다른 사람인 것 같지?
Because that’s really not the case...
실제로는 그렇지 않기 때문에...
It's okay
괜찮아
Oops
이런
You haven't looked good since just now
아까부터 표정이 안 좋아 보이던데
What happened?
무슨 일이 일어났나요?
I'm fine
난 괜찮아
don't worry
걱정하지 마세요
OK I'm not worried
알았어 걱정 안 해
After all, you said you didn't want me to worry about you at all.
결국 당신은 내가 당신에 대해 전혀 걱정하는 것을 원하지 않는다고 말했습니다.
Does that person want you not to worry about me at all?
그 사람은 당신이 나에 대해 전혀 걱정하지 않기를 바라나요?
what else did he say
그 사람 또 뭐라고 했어?
That person is you
그 사람이 바로 당신이에요
have you forgotten
잊었니?
You also personally promised not to let my hand go
너도 내 손 놓지 않겠다고 직접 약속했잖아
any drop of water
어떤 물방울이라도
You just accepted that promise like that?
방금 그 약속을 그렇게 받아들였나요?
Why do you climb on the roof at night these days?
요즘 왜 밤에 옥상에 오르나요?
I want to say that looking out from here might relieve my worries.
여기서 밖을 바라보면 걱정이 덜할 것 같다고 말하고 싶어요.
What is the reason for sending Hong Shi back through Zongxue?
Zongxue를 통해 Hong Shi를 다시 보내는 이유는 무엇입니까?
don't do anything
아무것도 하지 마세요
That's the only way to protect Eunjo
그게 은조를 지킬 수 있는 유일한 방법이야
You have to protect the mother you left behind.
당신은 당신이 두고 온 어머니를 보호해야 합니다.
I understand my situation
나는 내 상황을 이해한다
Aren't you going to go to a medical clinic?
병원에 가지 않을 건가요?
I heard that you witnessed the epidemic in the clinic
진료소에서 전염병을 목격했다고 들었습니다.
Is this serious?
심각한가요?
Yes
예
Is the source of the epidemic outside the capital a medical clinic?
수도 밖의 전염병의 근원지는 진료소인가?
No
아니요
It cannot be concluded that
이라고 결론지을 수는 없다
It’s up to me to judge
판단은 내가 하기 나름이다
A disease, right?
질병이죠?
What a good excuse
정말 좋은 변명이네요
Not a drop of water on my hands?
내 손에 물 한 방울도 묻지 않았나요?
You actually said such words through my mouth
넌 실제로 내 입으로 그런 말을 했어
Enzu
엔즈
Oops
이런
did you forget to get something
뭔가 가져오는 걸 잊었니?
I think you should know this
내 생각엔 네가 이걸 알아야 할 것 같아
Walked halfway and turned back
반쯤 걷다가 돌아섰다.
In short
요컨대
I heard this when I was drinking with the maid of the Department of Human Beings.
인간학과 가정부와 술을 마시다가 이런 말을 들었습니다.
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
I heard that the medical center will be closed tonight
오늘 밤에 의료 센터가 문을 닫는다고 들었어요
Everything will be bulldozed and burned to the ground
모든 것이 불도저로 불타 없어질 것이다
It's so pitiful. What should I do?
너무 불쌍해요. 어떻게 해야 하나요?
Doctor Hong?
홍박사님?
She said all she had to do was come to the officer for help.
그녀는 자신이 해야 할 일은 경찰관에게 도움을 청하는 것 뿐이라고 말했습니다.
You'll know who to report to
누구에게 보고해야 할지 알 수 있습니다.
Good
좋아
Everyone, get up quickly
다들 빨리 일어나
Get up quickly...
빨리 일어나...
Hurry up
서둘러
Doctor Hong
홍박사
We need to move the patients outside. Act quickly.
환자들을 밖으로 옮겨야 합니다. 신속하게 행동하십시오.
gold stone
금석
You go out and wake everyone up
네가 나가서 모두 깨워라
Everyone needs to escape from here
다들 여기서 탈출해야 해
Is this okay?
괜찮나요?
I am an animal and I am not responsible for judgment.
나는 동물이므로 판단에 대한 책임은 없습니다.
Just obey orders
명령에 복종할 뿐
Can you move?
움직일 수 있나요?
come out with me
나랑 같이 나오자
what happened
무슨 일이 있었나요?
I'll explain to you later
나중에 설명할게요
Let’s get the patient to the hospital quickly…
환자를 빨리 병원으로 이송하자…
Uncle Shi, your feet...
시 삼촌, 발이...
I was injured while hunting yesterday
어제 사냥하다가 다쳤어요
I'm fine
난 괜찮아
Soldiers so quickly...
군인들이 너무 빨리...
wait for me
나를 기다려
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
An order has been issued that patients here are to be shot
이곳의 환자들을 총살하라는 명령이 내려졌습니다
and a total blockade
그리고 전면 봉쇄
Run away quickly
빨리 도망쳐
Run to the back door
뒷문으로 달려가
Shunshi…
슌시…
You stay where you are, Shun Shi
넌 그 자리에 있어라, 순시
danger
위험
Dispose of them all
모두 처분하세요
catch me
나를 잡아라
You go quickly
빨리 가세요
As long as the child can survive
아이가 살아남을 수 있는 한
catch me quickly
빨리 잡아줘
If this continues, everyone will die.
계속 이러면 모두가 죽는다.
please leave quickly
빨리 떠나주세요
I'll be back. Just wait for me.
나는 돌아올 것이다. 나를 기다려주세요.
Doctor Hong
홍박사
Hong Eun-jo
홍은조
Can you still laugh?
아직도 웃을 수 있나요?
Your family is doing it for your own selfish reasons
당신의 가족은 당신의 이기적인 이유로 그런 일을 하고 있습니다.
The lives of so many people hang on a thread
수많은 사람들의 생명이 실에 매달려 있다
You know where this place is
여기가 어딘지 아시죠?
How dare you act so boldly?
어떻게 감히 그렇게 대담하게 행동합니까?
But I just can't control myself
하지만 난 내 자신을 통제할 수 없어
with you
너와 함께
I always forget fear
늘 두려움을 잊어요
Ji Tong is still alive
지통이 아직 살아있어요
See how protective you are of Ji Tong
당신이 Ji Tong을 얼마나 보호하는지 확인하세요
He must be a very important person to you.
그 사람은 당신에게 매우 중요한 사람임에 틀림없어요.
Everything about Ji Tong will be kept confidential
Ji Tong에 관한 모든 내용은 기밀로 유지됩니다.
You look after me from behind
뒤에서 나를 챙겨주는 너
What about you?
당신은 어떻습니까?
Are you leaving?
떠나시나요?
Where to go?
어디로 갈까요?